<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Boziuk on Boziuk</title>
    <link>http://www.boziuk.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Boziuk on Boziuk</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Thomas Boziuk</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Two-Phase Heat Transfer by Direct-Contact Condensation Using Directional Acoustic Actuation</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-condensation-ultrasound-therminic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-condensation-ultrasound-therminic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic enhancement of direct-contact condensation using capillary waves</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-condensation-capillary-ijhmt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-condensation-capillary-ijhmt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced boiling heat transfer on plain and featured surfaces using acoustic actuation</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-ijhmt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-ijhmt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Physical Society Division of Fluid Dynamics Gallery of Fluid Motion</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/post/aps-gfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/post/aps-gfm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Gallery of Fluid Motion is one of the most enjoyable aspects of the American Physical Society&amp;rsquo;s Division of Fluid Dynamics conferences. Although I had long admired the creativity of the entries, I never found the time to create a poster or video worthy of submission. In 2016, I devoted a significant effort to capturing a phenomena under investigation, and submitted a poster, which was one of the winners of the 2016 APS/DFD Gallery of Fluid Motion award winners in the poster category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A train of vapor bubbles is formed by ejection into a subcooled liquid pool. In the base flow, surface tension pinch-off drives a liquid &amp;ldquo;spear&amp;rdquo; through the center of the vapor bubble to form a vapor torus that leads to rapid condensation. Alternatively, using a directed 1.7 MHz pulsed acoustic beam early in the vapor bubble formation (and prior to pinch-off) exploits the liquid-vapor acoustic impedance mismatch to force a similar liquid &amp;ldquo;spear,&amp;rdquo; forming a vapor torus and accelerating the bubble collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.boziuk.com/img/aps_gfm_poster_boziuk_smith_glezer.png&#34; alt=&#34;Accelerated Condensation in an Ultrasonic Field - Boziuk Smith and Glezer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;links&#34;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gfm.aps.org/meetings/dfd-2016/57daf430b8ac311791000aad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Accelerated Condensation in an Ultrasonic Field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gfm.aps.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gallery of Fluid Motion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced boiling heat transfer on micromachined surfaces using acoustic actuation</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-textured-itherm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-textured-itherm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustically Enhanced Boiling</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-boiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-boiling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Boiling heat transfer on submerged textured heated surfaces is enhanced using ultrasound actuation. The heated surface is textured using an array of open microchannels that advantageously separate the nucleation sites on the surface and inhibit the transition to film boiling, which significantly increases the critical heat flux compared to a smooth surface of the same planform dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present investigation shows that the formation and evolution of vapor bubbles on the heated surface can be substantially altered by a highly directional ultrasound (1.7 MHz) beam, and lead to significant enhancement in heat transfer, including reduced surface superheat and increased CHF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat transfer enhancement characterized by changes in the boiling curve (i.e., superheat) varies with surface texturing and is also dependent on acoustic beam orientation relative to the surface texture pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustically Enhanced Condensation</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-condensation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-condensation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vapor bubbles are formed by direct injection into quiescent liquid in a sealed tank under controlled ambient pressure that varies from atmospheric to partial vacuum. The bubbles are injected vertically from a pressurized steam reservoir through nozzles of varying characteristic diameters, and the actuation is applied during different stages of the bubbles formation and advection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is shown that kHz range acoustic actuation leads to excitation of high-amplitude surface capillary (Faraday) waves at the vapor-liquid interface that significantly increases the condensation rate. The increase in condensation rate is affected by the surface waves that increase the mixing in the thermal boundary layer surrounding the bubble, which can be confirmed using Schlieren images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.boziuk.com/img/condensation_example_khz.png&#34; alt=&#34;khz enhanced condensation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultrasonic acoustic actuation may also be used for condensation enhancement. While kHz-range acoustic actuation typically couples to capillary instability of the vapor-liquid interface, ultrasonic (MHz-range) actuation leads to the formation of a liquid spout that penetrates into the vapor bubble and significantly increases its surface area and therefore condensation rate.  Focusing of the ultrasonic beam along the spout leads to ejection of small-scale droplets from that are propelled towards the vapor liquid interface and result in localized acceleration of the condensation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other FMRL Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/other-fmrl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/other-fmrl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustically enhanced boiling heat transfer </title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-physoffluid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/publication/enhanced-boiling-physoffluid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/various-personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/various-personal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some other personal projects of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sound board app with numpad keybinds. Useful for adding sound effects when recording, if the system sound is routed to an input (i.e., using jack, Cadence, Ardour, and other packages from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://kx.studio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;KXStudio project&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thomasboziuk/soundboard&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/thomasboziuk/soundboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Muse Finder&amp;rdquo; function set, reminiscent of weird websites from the 90&amp;rsquo;s. Based on someone&amp;rsquo;s birthday, you are able to find their &amp;ldquo;muses.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;
Who are someone&amp;rsquo;s muses? Well, they&amp;rsquo;re the two leading actors, of the top grossing movie, of the box-office week they were born. &lt;em&gt;Obviously!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thomasboziuk/muse_finder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/thomasboziuk/muse_finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
