<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Boziuk</title>
    <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Boziuk</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Thomas Boziuk</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.boziuk.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustically Enhanced Boiling</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-boiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-boiling/</guid>
      <description>Boiling heat transfer on submerged textured heated surfaces is enhanced using ultrasound actuation. The heated surface is textured using an array of open microchannels that advantageously separate the nucleation sites on the surface and inhibit the transition to film boiling, which significantly increases the critical heat flux compared to a smooth surface of the same planform dimensions.
The present investigation shows that the formation and evolution of vapor bubbles on the heated surface can be substantially altered by a highly directional ultrasound (1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustically Enhanced Condensation</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-condensation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/enhanced-condensation/</guid>
      <description>Vapor bubbles are formed by direct injection into quiescent liquid in a sealed tank under controlled ambient pressure that varies from atmospheric to partial vacuum. The bubbles are injected vertically from a pressurized steam reservoir through nozzles of varying characteristic diameters, and the actuation is applied during different stages of the bubbles formation and advection.
It is shown that kHz range acoustic actuation leads to excitation of high-amplitude surface capillary (Faraday) waves at the vapor-liquid interface that significantly increases the condensation rate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other FMRL Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/other-fmrl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/other-fmrl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Projects</title>
      <link>http://www.boziuk.com/project/various-personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.boziuk.com/project/various-personal/</guid>
      <description>Some other personal projects of interest:
 Sound board app with numpad keybinds. Useful for adding sound effects when recording, if the system sound is routed to an input (i.e., using jack, Cadence, Ardour, and other packages from the KXStudio project.)
https://github.com/thomasboziuk/soundboard
 &amp;ldquo;Muse Finder&amp;rdquo; function set, reminiscent of weird websites from the 90&amp;rsquo;s. Based on someone&amp;rsquo;s birthday, you are able to find their &amp;ldquo;muses.&amp;rdquo;
Who are someone&amp;rsquo;s muses? Well, they&amp;rsquo;re the two leading actors, of the top grossing movie, of the box-office week they were born.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>